

Aoife McCloskey

Ph.D.

Telephone +49 15204497023

Mail mccloska@tcd.ie

Location Berlin, Germany

Web linkedin.com/in/mccloska mccloska.github.io/

Programming

Python IDL R SQL HTML PHP C++

Skills

Data Mining
Probability/Statistics
Machine Learning
Sci-kit Learn
Pandas
Numpy
Linux
QGIS
Pytorch
Git

Executive Summary

Enthusiastic scientist with extensive experience in **computer programming**, **mathematics** and **statistics**. Developed a novel **forecasting model** that improved the forecasting of solar flares using modern **machine learning** techniques. **Co-founded** an educational company (Codify Ltd.) that taught **Python programming** courses to adults. Exceptional ability to **communicate complex ideas** and concepts to a wide range of audiences. Passionate about understanding the stories that lie within data and using these insights to provide solutions to **challenging real-world problems**.

Relevant Experience

2020-2022 Machine Learning for Space \

Machine Learning for Space Weather Dept. of Space Weather Impact, DLR Carried out ML research and led a project on the topic of Space Weather impacts on German infrastructure & satellites

- Led a team on a project to assess the impact of space weather on the German Electricity Network. Within 1 year developed a geospatial model that estimated the vulnerability of the power grid to geomagnetic disturbances using SQL, QGIS & Scipy.
- Developed a new ML method to predict solar wind arrival timing for satellites which led to >50% improvement over previous methods.
- Led my own research project to continue to develop & improve my flare forecasting model. Applied additional ML techniques that led to a two-fold increase in the prediction power of the model.

2014-2019 PhD Researcher

Astrophysics Research Group, Trinity College Dublin

Carried out research in the area of Space Weather to improve the forecasting of Solar Flares

Statistical Flare Forecasting Project

- Cleaned, analysed and optimised 30+ years of historical data catalogues using Python libraries e.g., Pandas, Numpy
- Developed a new predictive model for solar flares using a combination of statistical techniques and machine learning methods (e.g. K-Nearest Neighbour, Logistic Regression, Random Forests etc.) via Sci-Kit Learn
- Quantified the improvement and impact of my forecasting models using verification techniques (i.e. skill scores) which yielded a >30% improvement over previous models.

SolarMonitor Website Developer

- Collaborated with an international team in developing a website that provided real-time information on solar activity at <u>SolarMonitor.org</u>.
- Developed full-stack code to improve the stability and efficiency of the data pipeline, gained experience using version-control software (Git) and implemented my new flare forecasting model (Flare Prediction System) which runs forecasts daily.

2016-2018 Co-Founder

Codify Ltd.

Co-founded Codify Ltd. which provided data science and Python programming workshops in Dublin for adults.`

- Created curricula for courses, including an 8-week "Introduction to Python" and 3-day intensive "Python for Scientists" programme.
- Organised 50+ classes and taught 200+ students to date.
- Mentored students in the creation of their own data science projects including: NLP, House Price Prediction using ML, Twitter Bots and NYPD Data Analysis

Languages

English (Fluent) German (Level A2/B1)

Awards

2014-2018

Irish Research Council Postgraduate Scholarship

2018

US Space Weather Workshop Student Travel Award

2015

Trinity College Dublin PG Teaching Excellence Award

2012 & 2013

Trinity College Dublin First Class Book Prize

Interests

Dancing Yoga 🔊

Meditation 4

Music &

Travel *

Education

2014-2018 Ph.D. in Astrophysics Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

Funded by the Irish Research Council Postgraduate Scholarship Program Thesis: Magnetic Characteristics of Sunspot Groups and their Role in

Producing Adverse Space Weather

2014-2015 Postgraduate Certificate in Statistics, I

Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

35 ECT course in frequentist statistics

2010-2014 B.A. Mod. in Astrophysics, II.I Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

Thesis: Connecting Geomagnetic Storms in Ireland to Coronal Mass

Ejections

Publications

Baumann, C., McCloskey, A. E. (2021)

"Timing of the solar wind propagation delay between L1 and Earth based on machine learning"

Journal of Space Weather and Space Climate, 11, 41

Leka, K. D., Park, S. H., [et. al, including McCloskey, A. E.] (2019)

"Comparison of Flare Forecasting Methods. II. Benchmarks, Metrics and Performance Results for Operational Solar Flare Forecasting Systems"

The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series

McCloskey, A. E., Gallagher, P. T., Bloomfield, D. S. (2018)

"Flare forecasting using the evolution of McIntosh sunspot classifications"

Journal of Space Weather and Space Climate, 8, A34

McCloskey, A. E., Gallagher, P. T., Bloomfield, D. S. (2016)

"Flaring rates and the evolution of sunspot group McIntosh classifications"

Solar Physics, 291, 6, 1711-1738

References

Conferences, Events & Communication

Available Upon Request

Oct 2019 **Predict Conference** Dublin, Ireland

Session host at Europe's leading Predict Data Science Conference (1000+

attendees)

2014-2017 **Sunspotter Project** Dublin, Ireland

Visited 20+ primary & secondary schools all over Ireland presenting workshops about the importance of sunspots and their role in Space

Weather.

Feb 2017 **Bright Club** Dublin, Ireland

Invited to give a talk/stand-up comedy gig about my field of research to an

audience of 100+ people

Mercury Transit 2016 May 2016

Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

Organised and co-hosted an event that invited the public (>1000 attendees) to come and witness the transit of Mercury in Trinity College Dublin. Event gained press coverage and was covered in the national newspapers.

Mar 2015 Solar Eclipse 2015 Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

Organised and co-hosted a public event that invited the public (>1000 attendees) to come and view the solar eclipse in Trinity College Dublin. Event gained significant press coverage and was covered on the national

news (RTE).